Okay.
I hope we are live here, live streaming.
So sort of set up for it, but they made a new
session. So I guess we'll find out and hope this is broadcasting.
Alright, anyway, so we are
in
ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av right now, so חודש טוב Chodesh
Tov and everything that the nine days
is
about, you know, we'll keep that in mind. So, but today's דף
Daf is where we are is ס"ו Samech Vav of עמוד א'.
Amud Aleph. We are two lines from the bottom.
And we have been having a מחלוקת Machlokes between רבה Rabbah and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef whether יאוש Ye'ush works, basically specifically in the
case of a גנב Ganav to acquire an object. רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says יאוש Ye'ush has no effect at all, so the גנב
Ganav does not acquire it, but רבה Rabbah does. He says that
it affects a קנין Kinyan for the גנב. Ganav. And we talked
about different types of קניינים Kinyanim yesterday like שינוי מעשה, Shinui Maaseh,
שינוי השם, Shinui Hashem, if those are enough of a שינוי Shinui
to affect an acquisition.
So picking up from this spot, איתיביה רב יוסף לרבה. Aisvei Rav
Yosef l'Rabbah. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef who holds that it has
no effect questions רבה Rabbah who holds that it does. So גזל
חמץ ועבר עליו הפסח, Gazeil Chametz V'avar Alav HaPesach, so let's say
somebody stole someone else's חמץ Chametz and now this was right before
פסח Pesach and now פסח Pesach has
gone,
has come and gone. And now it's after פסח. Pesach. So now
we know that or we should know we need to know that
if there is חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח, Chametz She'avar Alav HaPesach, if
one has חמץ Chametz in one's possession through the holiday of פסח
Pesach and it has not, you know, מפקיר Mafkir it, has not
gotten rid of it, has not sold it, has not anything, and
just kept it the whole time, so it's the same חמץ Chametz
before and the same חמץ Chametz after, but there's a קנס Knas
from the רבנן Rabbanan that it's now like worthless. You can't do
anything with it. You can't eat it, you can't sell it, you
can't anything. So that's the קנס Knas because they don't want you
to do these kind of things. So let's say someone stole someone
else's חמץ Chametz and now פסח Pesach has come and gone and
now it's after פסח, Pesach,
but nevertheless, you know, you have the stolen חמץ. Chametz. So what
do you do, right? If I stole something I have to give
it back. But the problem is it's worthless even to the other
guy. It's worthless to anybody. It's worthless to the גנב, Ganav, it's
worthless to the original owner because even if it's not your fault,
if there was חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח Chametz She'avar Alav HaPesach you
are stuck, you know, it is just forbidden. Just think of it
as, you know, like a שור הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, no one can
use it. So you have to give it back. So alright, so
you give it back. אמר לו הרי שלך לפניך. Amar lo harey
shelcha lefanecha. Here it is, take it. Now, the guy can't use
it, but that's what you can do. But the question is האי
כי מטי עידן איסורא ודאי מיאש. Hai kemati idan issura vadai mi'ayash.
So certainly the guy who owns it, the guy from whom the
חמץ Chametz was stolen
once, you know, let's say this was like six months before פסח.
Pesach. Alright, I hope I get it back, I hope I get
it back, I hope I get it back. Alright, now it's like
a minute before פסח. Pesach. I don't even want it back. You
know what I mean? Like, you know, I'm certainly not getting it
back now, and even if I do, what good is it going
to do me? So הוא מיאש. Hu mi'ayash. He's like, ah forget
it, I'm writing it off. So וודאי מיאש, Vadai mi'ayash, but ואי
סלקא דעתך יאוש קנה, Ve'i salka dach-tach ye'ush koneh, but if יאוש
Ye'ush is קונה, Koneh, so אמאי אמר לו הרי שלך לפניך? Amay
amar lo harey shelcha lefanecha? דמי מעליא בעי לשלומי ליה. Damei malya
ba'ei l'shalumei lei. You can't just give it back. You have to
pay him, right? To, you know, like I stole something I got
to pay you for it. I can't just say הרי שלך לפניך,
Harey shelcha lefanecha, especially since if it was always yours I can
give it back to you, right? But if it was wasn't yours,
if it now has transitioned to be mine through your, through your
יאוש, Ye'ush, now I have to pay you for it just like
with anything else.
So that's his question. So since he can say הרי שלך לפניך,
Harey shelcha lefanecha, then it seems to be that יאוש Ye'ush is
not קונה, Koneh,
right?
So אמר ליה כי קאמינא אנא זה מתייאש וזה רוצה לקנות, האי
זה מתייאש וזה אינו רוצה לקנות. Amar lei ki kamina ana zeh
mityayesh vezeh rotzeh liknot, hai zeh mityayesh vezeh eino rotzeh liknot. Yeah,
I mean I say that in a regular case. Like in a
normal case, you know, there are two parties to the, for lack
of a better word, I'll call it transaction, but two parties to
an event is a bit I guess how I'd say. So in
the regular case the גנב Ganav really wants to have something, right?
That's why he's stealing it.
So then at some point the נגזל, Nigzal, the guy from whom
it was stolen, gives it up. So in the case of חמץ
Chametz though, the גנב Ganav does not want to have חמץ שעבר
עליו הפסח Chametz She'avar Alav HaPesach because then he'd be עובר אדאורייתא,
Over A-De'Oraita, right? You can't have חמץ. Chametz. And so in a
normal case, yes, why is, I do hold that יאוש Ye'ush works
and that's the way it would work were this not חמץ שעבר
עליו הפסח. Chametz She'avar Alav HaPesach. The יאוש Ye'ush would work again
because the owner wants to
give up his ownership through just despairing and the guy who stole
it, the גנב Ganav wants to have it. That's why he's stealing
it. But in חמץ Chametz in פסח Pesach it's different because, you
know, it's pretty weighty. You know, alright maybe. Okay, but the כרת,
karet, you know, is a—is another story because to have חמץ chometz
on פסח Pesach is a lot worse.
Isn't that a bit of a particular case?
Because—yeah, that's what he's saying. He's saying exactly that.
This is a particular case. You can't question me on this case
because in this case the גנב ganav does not
want it and neither does the owner want it. No one wants
it.
Is it really a question of despair in that case? Is what
I'm saying.
Does he really
say I'm getting rid of that either way, whoever's got it, I
don't want it.
Well, I mean, from the perspective of the owner, like in despair,
it's sort
of—I hear what you're saying. It is a little bit different, but
the effect would still be the same. Whether he's giving up ownership
of it because he really doesn't want it or whether he's despairing
of getting it back, he still—he's still giving up ownership. But, you
know, focus more on the other end of the transaction, which is
the גנב ganav doesn't want it either, or, you know, we assume
he doesn't want it, even though he's a גנב. ganav. Maybe he
wanted it before, but, you know, now he certainly doesn't. But when
he wanted it before, the owner never despaired. You know what I
mean? So, you know, but now when the owner's despairing, he doesn't
want it either. So that's why he can say הרי שלך לפניך
harei shelcha lefanecha because it still is always, you know, quote-unquote, you
know, it wasn't his, the גנב, ganav, so he can just give
it back. So you can't ask me on that. He says, אביי
Abaye
to
רבא, Rava, another question. קורבנו ולא הגזול. korbano velo hagezul. So, you
know, a קורבן, korban, whatever, in the case of any קורבן korban
that one brings, it has to be your קורבן. korban. So it's
your קורבן korban as opposed to a stolen one. הכי דמי? heichi
dami? So
and here we're thinking right now that what do we mean like,
you know, and not a stolen one? So like let's say I
steal your sheep and now I want to make it into a
קורבן. korban. So that's what we think it's talking about. So, you
know, I was גוזל gozel a regular, you know, חולין chullin animal
and now I want to bring it as a קורבן korban for
myself.
So what kind of case are you talking about? הכי דמי? אילימא
לפני יאוש למה לי קרא. heichi dami? elima lifnei yeush lama li
kra. If the original owner never despaired, then of course it won't
work. פשיטא. pshita. It's obvious that I can't bring a stolen animal
as a קורבן. korban. God would want such a thing? God would
never accept such a thing. אלא לאו אחר יאוש? ella lav achar
yeush? No, nevertheless, still אחר יאוש. achar yeush. ושמע מינה יאוש לא
קני. ushma mina yeush lo kani. And even so, I still can't
bring it because, meaning why? Because, you know, because if יאוש yeush
worked, then it would be קורבנו. korbano. It would be my קורבן.
korban. If you despaired of it, then it's my קורבן. korban. Yeah,
I stole it, okay, but, you know, but still at least my
קורבן. korban. So since the פסוק pasuk is going out of its
way to tell you ולא הגזול, velo hagezul, it's coming to teach
you that even after יאוש, yeush, יאוש yeush doesn't work and I
still can't bring it. So
אמר ליה רבא. amar leh Rava. So he said, all right, well
if that's what you want to say, לטעמיך הא דתני משכבו, leta'ameich
ha detani mishkavo, like for any of these טומאות, tumos, like a
משכב הזב mishkav hazav or whatever, so משכבו ולא הגזול. mishkavo velo
hagezul. הכי דמי? heichi dami?
So would you say the same thing? אילימא דגזל עמרא ועבדיה משכבו?
elima degazal amra ve'avdeih mishkavo?
Let's say, you know, I stole whatever it was, like a ball
of wool and I made it into a bed, a blanket. מי
איכא למאן דאמר שינוי מעשה לא קני? mi ika leman de'amar shinui
ma'aseh lo kani? Then certainly it would be mine. I mean because,
you know, again in the case of—in the case of stealing חמץ,
chometz, let's say there's no שינוי מעשה. shinui ma'aseh. It's the same,
you know, bagel as it was a second ago. But in the
case of stealing a ball of unprocessed, you know, wool and now
I, you know, I weave it, I dye it, I this, I
that, you know, I made it into a blanket. It's completely different.
You know, you would never recognize the ball of wool anymore. Now
it looks like a bed, you know, or a blanket. So everyone
would say that שינוי מעשה shinui ma'aseh works. So how would you
explain that case? אלא מאי אית לך למימר? ella mai it lach
lemimar? דגזל משכב דחבריה. degazal mishkav dechavreih. No, so we're not talking
about a שינוי מעשה. shinui ma'aseh. We're talking about a case where
I actually—literally stole like his bed, right? So it comes to teach
you like let's say
I stole your bed and, you know, and I'm טמא, tamei, then
I, you know, sleep on it. Then it actually does not become
טמא tamei if it's a stolen bed. That's interesting. So it's not
like, you know, טומאה tumah automatically inheres to the object. It has
to be my object from—in which טומאה tumah can, you know, inhere.
In other words, you can still sit on it and if you're
טמא tamei and if it's my object and it will become טמא,
tamei, but if I steal it, you know, then that changes everything.
הכי נמי דגזל קורבן דחבריה. hachi nami degazal korban dechavreih. So so
too, meaning like you were mistaking the
case
that the—that you know, it was חולין chullin and then, you know,
then it was יאוש yeush and all that. No, no, no. I
just stole the קורבן korban of somebody and then I want to
bring it. So that's what it's telling you: קורבנו ולא הגזול. korbano
velo hagezul.
So and, you know, why—so then why doesn't it work? So, you
know, I mean basically, like if it's already a קורבן, korban, then
it's not even yours anymore. You know what I mean? Like it's
kind of God's by that point. So that's why, you know, God
doesn't give up ownership so easily. So basically, I mean that's the
way I'd explain it. So
the point being that when, you know, יאוש yeush is—is
not—it's not like an applicable case. So
in a nor—you know, you gotta—so basically he asks two questions. One
is from the חמץ chometz case. He said that's not a normal
case because the גנב ganav doesn't want to acquire it. So יאוש,
yeush, you know, is just
not—it's not a factor here because either there was or wasn't יאוש,
yeush, the גנב ganav doesn't want it, so it won't be his.
And then קורבן, korban, and then the case of קורבן, korban, you
know, we're talking about a stolen קורבן korban and it's in God's—God's
hands. hands, so יאוש yei'ush doesn't count there either.
So yeah, because רש''י Rashi explains, it's a good רש''י, Rashi, just,
you know, if you don't have a bolded, it's so much easier
if you have bolded רש''י'ס, Rashis, but it's right sort of where,
I don't know how to explain it, but it's, you know, like
ten lines down on the narrow lines.
לשנא אחריתא דגזל קרבן אחר שהוקדש אפילו אחר יאוש לא קנייה. Lishna
acharita degazal korban achar shehukdash afilu achar yei'ush lo kanyei. Even if
there was יאוש, yei'ush, the גנב ganav still doesn't acquire it. קרבן
אינו נגזל, Korban eino nigzal, so you can't really steal a קרבן.
korban. דהיכא דאיתיה בגיזא דרחמנא איתיה. Deheicha de'iseih begaza derachamana iseih. So
it's in God's hands. God is everywhere. So it's not even your
friend's קרבן korban at this point, it's God's קרבן, korban, and you
know, God's everywhere. You know what I mean? So like, you know,
you're not stealing it from him.
So that so קרבן korban so that doesn't apply either in terms
of יאוש yei'ush and קונה. koneh. Okay, fine. So we these were
questions on רבא, Rava, right, who who was saying that יאוש yei'ush
is קונה, koneh, and we said, oh, well, it seems like it
didn't from the קרבן korban case and from the פסח Pesach case,
and we answered those. Now we're going to ask the other way,
to רב יוסף Rav Yosef who says יאוש yei'ush is not קונה.
koneh. איתיביה אביי לרב יוסף. Eisvei Abaye le-Rav Yosef. So this is
going to be from a טומאה tumah perspective. So, you know, there's
certain things that are מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tumah, but even things that are, like, not necessarily right
away, let's say a piece of leather. If it's just like a
regular piece of leather and nothing's happened to it, and, you know,
all it's been is skin from the animal, it's not מקבל טומאה
mekabel tumah in its raw state. I could use it, let's say,
as a mat, you know, like think about like the bearskin rug
type of thing, right, you know, you just kind of just put
it there.
So if I just did that, then it would be finished. The
idea is it's not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah until it's like a
finished object. So finished is sort of relative, right? It could be
if, you know, if I want it to be like a shoe,
right, you know, you can't have this piece of leather sitting there.
It's got to be shaped, it's got to be tanned, it's got
to be this, it's got to be that, sewn, stitched, you know,
the whole deal. So in its raw state then it wouldn't be
anything, wouldn't become טמא. tamei. But if it was something that I
wanted to use for a mat, then in its raw state it
would become טמא. tamei. So it all depends on how finished it
is and what my intention is.
So let's say it's the regular householder, עורות של בעל הבית מחשבה
מטמאתן. Oros shel ba'al habayis machshavah metame'asan. So if I'm thinking it's
done, now it's a כלי kli and can potentially become טמא. tamei.
ושל עבדן אין מחשבה מטמאתן. Veshel avdan ein machshavah metame'asan. But if
it's like the guy who's a leather worker, makes no difference what
he thinks, you know, because like the end, it depends on what
the end user wants to use it for. If he's thinking it's
done, but then I come in and say no, it's not done,
you know, I want this to be a pair of shoes and
it's not done. So him thinking that it's done won't have any
difference. של גנב מחשבה מטמאתן. Shel ganav machshavah metame'asan. If someone steals
it and his מחשבה machshavah does cause it to become טמא, tamei,
so then that and this is the question, right? How can his
מחשבה machshavah cause it to become טמא tamei if יאוש yei'ush is
not קונה, koneh, right? רב יוסף Rav Yosef holds that יאוש yei'ush
is not קונה, koneh, but clearly it is קונה koneh if the
if the גנב ganav when if what
if his intentions and thoughts make a difference. של גזלן אין מחשבה
מטמאתן. Shel gazlan ein machshavah metame'asan. For a גזלן gazlan his מחשבה
machshavah does not, why? Because he thinks, you know, look, I saw
who robbed me, you know, I can get it back. So the
owner is not מיאש miya'esh on it. רב שמעון אומר חילוף הדברים.
Rabbi Shimon omer chiluf hadevarim. You know, the opposite. של גזלן מחשבה
מטמאתן. Shel gazlan machshavah metame'asan. The גזלן gazlan does, his מחשבה machshavah
does is מטמא metamei because someone's so brazen, you know, and steals
it from you, he's like, I'm never going to get it back,
this guy's too powerful for me. ושל גנב אין מחשבה מטמאתן. Veshel
ganav ein machshavah metame'asan. But but the גנב ganav it isn't because
you know the owner will think it will he he hasn't given
up hope yet. דלא ידע דאיאשוא בעלים. Dilo yada de'iya'ashu ba'alim. You
know, the police investigation will uncover who stole it and I'll get
it back.
Anyway, but the point is, whether you hold it's a גנב ganav
or גזלן, gazlan, it certainly works for one of them, you know,
on the idea is that he is קונה. koneh. So רב יוסף
Rav Yosef holds he isn't קונה. koneh. שמע מינה יאוש קונה. Shema
mina yei'ush kaneh. So אמר ליה הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון
שקיצען. Amar leih hacha bemai askinan kegon shekitze'an. You know, it's not
just the fact that he stole it and you know, now it's
his, but he did a שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh on it. קיצען.
Kitze'an. So he cut it up, he cut it up, you know,
he trimmed it a little bit.
So the
the point is that
you need both of these. You need the מעשה ma'aseh and the
יאוש yei'ush because like basically like קיצען kitze'an is not much of
anything. You sort of like trimmed it a little bit. You know
what I mean? It's not like you made it in my case
from like a piece of leather to a shoe, that's like a
real big deal. Here you trimmed it a little bit. It's not
much of a it's sort of like on the periphery of being
a real שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh because we're already holding the שינוי
מעשה shinnui ma'aseh we're already
kind
of
are operating on the assumption that שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh is enough
potentially by itself. But really do a שינוי מעשה, shinnui ma'aseh, you
know, like I take your, you know, wheat and turn it into
flour, that's a real שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh then it is mine
even if it weren't נתייאשו. nisya'ashu. Now it's like something totally different.
So this is sort of like a weak שינוי מעשה. shinnui ma'aseh.
So just trimming it a little bit, it doesn't look that much
different. So you know, it was a piece of whatever high two
feet long, now it's like one feet, you know, eleven inches long,
big deal, right? So that's why you need this with this type
of שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh you need a שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh
with a יאוש. yei'ush. So that's why we're saying whatever it is,
אחר נתייאשו achar nisya'ashu for the גנב ganav or the גזלן, gazlan,
but the point being that there's a שינוי מעשה shinnui ma'aseh and
יאוש yei'ush and so you basically basically got the case wrong. So
you're saying like oh like you know ייאוש ye'ush itself you're asking
me, it seems like ייאוש ye'ush itself is קונה koneh and I
hold it isn't. So the case really isn't just ייאוש, ye'ush, the
case is ייאוש ye'ush and a little bit of a שינוי מעשה
shinnuy ma'aseh and that's why he's קונה. koneh. So your case the
case you're asking me is different, right? In a regular case, let's
say there was no שינוי shinnuy at all, מעשה, ma'aseh, let's say
he didn't do anything,
then ייאוש ye'ush wouldn't work and I'd be fine. This משנה mishnah
we're saying ייאוש ye'ush does work is because there's a שינוי מעשה,
shinnuy ma'aseh, I didn't say it but that's our case. So מתקיף
לה matkif lah רבה בר רב חנן, Rabba bar Rav Chanan, והלא
איצבא שנו כאן,
ve-halo itzba
shanu kan, ואיצבא לא צריכה קיצועא. ve-itzba lo tzericha kitzu'a. What do
you mean the case we're talking about, you know, which is where
you did this, you know, trimming a little bit? No, that's not
the case. You know, basically what רש"י Rashi is from a משנה
mishnah that comes a lot later and there's it's like sort of
like a longer משנה. mishnah. So this whole case about the עורות
של בעל הבית מחשבה מטמאתן, orot shel ba'al ha-bayit machshavah metama'atan, the
מחשבה machshavah of the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit and the גנב ganav
and the גזלן, gazlan,
that he's saying is from a case, that is like the end
of a discussion
previous. And the discussion previous was talking about an איצבא, itzba, like
a tray of some sort. And this איצבא itzba does not even
need this קיצוע. kitzu'a. So you're saying the whole case is where
there was some sort of trimming involved, but we're talking about, but
that's not what the case is. If you just look at the
case, he's saying, if you just look at the case it's not
that case. איצבא לא צריכה קיצוע, itzba lo tzericha kitzu'a, דתנן, de-tenan,
and now he's quoting the preceding discussion to this עורות orot case,
כל מקום שאין חסרון מלאכה מחשבה מטמאתן. kol makom she-ein chisron melachah
machshavah metama'atan. You know, if there's no more that needs to be
done to this piece of leather, then מחשבה machshavah is sufficient. יש
חסרון מלאכה אין מחשבה מטמאתן. yesh chisron melachah ein מחשבה metama'atan. If
there's a little bit of מלאכה melachah to do left, still something
to do here, then my מחשבה machshavah will not cause it to
become טמא tamei because, you know, it's not finished yet, it has
to be done to need to think that it is done, has
actually really be done. חוץ מן האיצבא, chutz min ha-itzba, except for
an איצבא, itzba, and then it goes on, you know, to that
case. So in an איצבא, itzba, we don't, you know, in an
איצבא itzba the חסרון מלאכה chisron melachah is not a factor, right?
He's saying basically that if there's חסרון מלאכה chisron melachah then that
needs to be done for it to become טמא tamei except for
an איצבא itzba which doesn't need any מלאכה. melachah. So you're saying
oh no no the case is different because there needs to be
some מלאכה melachah done to this case and that's why ייאוש ye'ush
itself is not sufficient, but in this case no מלאכה melachah needs
to be done. So ייאוש ye'ush itself should be sufficient and we
see that it is and you hold it doesn't work, but the
case is that it does work and that you don't need any
מלאכה. melachah. Are we all clear? Because the case was that the
גנב ganav can through his מחשבה machshavah cause it to cause it
to become
טמא. tamei. So it is because the guy
was מתייאש. mitya'esh. So that's a question
of רב יוסף
Rav
Yosef who holds ייאוש ye'ush has no effect because clearly it does
because the גנב ganav can cause it
to become
טמא tamei and מלאכה melachah is not a factor here because there's
no מלאכה melachah that needs to be done over here. So what
do you have to say? So how do you answer this? You
know, if you want to answer רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, how can
he reconcile this משנה mishnah that seems to say that ייאוש ye'ush
is effective with רב יוסף's Rav Yosef position that holds that ייאוש
ye'ush has no effect? אלא אמר רבא האי מילתא קשיא ליה לרבא
מרב יוסף עשרין ותרין שנין. ela amar Rava hai milta kashya leh
le-Rava me-Rav Yosef esrin ve-tartein shanin. So you know what, as a
matter of fact there was an outstanding question that רבא Rava had
been bothering רב יוסף Rav Yosef with for twenty-two years.
ולא איפרקא, ve-lo ifreka, and he had no answer. יתבינן אדרשידיה, itvinan
adarshideih, you know, I guess they're like, hey hey you know top
question, what's the answer? You know, let's so I can just envision
that. אידי לא הוי ליה שינוי עד דיתבי רב יוסף ברישא ופרקה.
idi lo havei leh shinnuy ad de-itvei Rav Yosef be-reisha u-farkeih.
So until רב יוסף Rav Yosef became, it's very interesting, until רב
יוסף Rav Yosef became the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, then then he
was able to answer it. So like I guess there's some sort
of like you might have to say that there was some sort
of סיעתא דשמיא, siyata de-shamaya, you know, that once he you know
once he became in a more exalted position he was able to
answer these questions because you know you don't want a ראש ישיבה
Rosh Yeshiva that can be stumped. You know what I mean? So
I guess that's I
guess
that's what you can read into this. Anyway, but the point is
so this was an outstanding question and but at some point he
managed to answer it or at least he at least he thinks
he managed to answer it, we'll see. שינוי השם כשינוי מעשה דמי.
shinnuy ha-shem ke-shinnuy ma'aseh dami. You know yeah okay.
רב יוסף's Rav Yosef point is that ייאוש ye'ush in isolation, let's
say you don't need anything else, remember we talked about this yesterday,
there's something called שינוי מעשה, shinnuy ma'aseh, something called שינוי השם, shinnuy
ha-shem, right? All these are שינויים. shinnuyim. But let's say you don't
have any of that, like you know like I stole your you
know sheep and it's still a sheep and it's you know the
same year-old sheep that it always was, you know like two days
later, right? You know I didn't do anything, it didn't become an
adult or or I stole an adult ram, whatever, right? I didn't
do anything, I didn't שחט, shachat, I didn't this, it's not meat,
it's an alive living animal, then that's the debate רב יוסף Rav
Yosef would say where whether ייאוש ye'ush is קונה koneh or not.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef will hold that it isn't and you know
others might hold that it does. But in this case over here
with the leather
it's even though we said that you don't necessarily necessarily the מעשה
ma'aseh is is not a factor over here because it doesn't make
a difference, but there nevertheless is a שינוי השם. shinnuy hashem. And
שינוי השם shinnuy hashem is as good as a שינוי מעשה, shinnuy
ma'aseh, and that's a שינוי shinnuy enough. So in other words it's
not just a ייאוש, ye'ush, right? There's now something different. Why? Because
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama התם מעיקרא אצי והשתא כלים. hatam me'ikara atzei
ve-hashta keilim.
So
in the case of like let's say whatever
like
I steal a piece of wood and make it into a bowl,
right? So at the beginning it was a piece of wood and
now it's a bowl. So שינוי השם נמי מעיקרא קרו ליה משכא
והשתא ארבזא, shinnuy hashem nami me'ikara koro lei mashka ve-hashta arvezeh, right?
So if it's a שינוי מעשה, shinnuy ma'aseh, like you know like
its a piece of wood and hollow it out and you know
and I make it into a bowl okay now there's a שינוי
מעשה. shinnuy ma'aseh. But שינוי השם shinnuy hashem is the same thing,
like you know before it was just like a piece of leather,
now it's a tray, it's a mat, it's a this, it's a
that, right? So now you call it something different, you know in
other words let's say I put a you know a tablecloth like
on my table would you call it you know would you call
it like a piece of cotton no you call it tablecloth, right?
So before this leather when it was in you know the guy's
you know whatever workshop it was a piece of leather but now
that you're putting it in your house and you know you're using
it as a tray or as a mat or whatever you want
or whatever you want now now it's a tray it's a mat
you know you buy it and you buy it as a tray
and a mat.
So yeah it still kind of looks the same but now it's
called something different and sometimes only in name, right? So and this
is one of those cases. So if again if it was just
like the same animal it was like a you know a ram
yesterday and a ram today there wouldn't be שינוי השם shinnuy hashem
there wouldn't be שינוי מעשה. shinnuy ma'aseh. But over here you know
now that it's actually being used as as an object it's even
though there wasn't a physical change that happened to it it's a
name change and that is enough. A name change is is good
as an an act that's that's done on something and that's why
it's not just a straight ייאוש ye'ush case because now it's a
שינוי shinnuy case too. But whether if it was just a straight
ייאוש ye'ush case רב יוסף Rav Yosef would still maintain that ייאוש
ye'ush wouldn't work. So you know your question he's saying is not
a question because you know yeah the גנב ganaf thought about something
and it seems that that's sufficient that's because yeah it's it's a
thinking and now it's called something different and it's considered to be
a good enough שינוי shinnuy that that through with ייאוש ye'ush it
works. So it's a שינוי shinnuy plus ייאוש ye'ush not just a
straight ייאוש ye'ush case.
Yeah it's like people who are ill change their name. Is it...
yeah right right you change
the situation
so it's a similar kind of idea.
Good point.
So we're all good so far? All right I'm going on.
Okay so basically we're trying to say is that okay that like
if it's called something else then that's like a change, right? So
that's and that's you know and that's different. But he questions א
מריש, a mareish, right? So this is so this is what רב
יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's answer was, right? So you know he figured this
out over 22 years and now he became the ראש ישיבה. Rosh
Yeshiva. But the question is מריש אבני דאיכא שינוי השם דמעיקרא כשורה
והשתא טפלא. mareish avi mi d'ika shinnuy hashem d'me'ikara keshura ve-hashta tafala.
And this is a famous case that דתנן מריש הגזול שבנאו בבירה
ישנה לו דמו מפני תקנת השבים. detnan mareish hagazul shebano bebira yishnotu
d'mo mipnei takanat hashavim. So the idea is like let's say you
have let's say you know you're I go
you own a Home Depot store and you know you you're selling
these two-by-fours. I go in and I steal one and I put
it in my roof, you know as a beam, like a rafter
now, right? Like top of my roof. But the same thing like
they didn't even do anything. I didn't like you know I didn't
dye it, I didn't shape it, there's no molding on it, there's
no nothing, I just like you know used it to to support
my you know the eaves of my house, the roof or rafter
whatever, right? So now now it's in there so before it was
a two-by-four now it's like my roof, right? And nevertheless we we
we hold that that if let's say I I I steal it
and I want to do תשובה, teshuvah, right? I really shouldn't have
stolen your your two-by-four. But like listen it's like now again it's
part of my house so I'm not going to tear down my
house just to give back your two-by-four, right? So what do you
do? I'm supposed to give back ideally what I stole, right? But
I can't. So all right so fine so you know we should
we would say you know that I should tear down my house
but we're not going to say that because then no one's going
to say forget it I'm not going to even bother giving it
back if I have to tear down my house to give him
back his stupid two-by-four. So fine so so I'll pay you for
it, right? You really want your your beam back but it's okay
you know I'll pay you the value for your beam. So because
תקנת השבים takanat hashavim because we want to make it easier for
people to do תשובה teshuvah and not have to go through tearing
down their house to give back something. So that seems to be
the only reason, right? Were it not for תקנת השבים takanat hashavim
we would say you do have to do it. But wait a
minute weren't you saying before that the שינוי השם shinnuy hashem would
be mine, right? Why would I have to give you back the
piece of wood? It's not yours anymore, it's my wood, right? Before
it was a two-by-four now it's my roof, right? טעמא מפני תקנת
השבים הא לאו הכי הדר בעיניה ta'ama mipnei takanat hashavim ha lav
hachi hadar be-einei you would have to give it back. So this
is the question of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, right? Because you would
have to give it back and ייאוש ye'ush would not be sufficient
even with the even with the שינוי השם shinnuy hashem and רב
יוסף Rav Yosef was trying to say that שינוי השם shinnuy hashem
is sufficient. So what do you do about that? אמר יוסף מריש
שמו עליו. amar Yosef mareish shemo alav. No,
because it's you're saying that it's a new name but it really
isn't, it's still it's still the same name. דתניא ועולתה הבית אלו
המלטטין ועובין אלו המרשות. detanya ve-aulta habayit elu ha-melatetin ve-huvin elu ha-marshot.
Anyway and then יחזקאל'ס Yechezkel's talking about the third... Anyway, in יחזקאל
Yechezkel is talking about the third בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and and
it's talking about building it and it's talking about עבים uvim like
beams and whatever it is, but you know but the question and
the explanation is these are מראי שם, marei shem, these are these
beams. So meaning that even though it's the roof, it's still called
beams. So the point is that the beam is still considered a
beam even if I put it in my roof. It's not really
a שינוי השם. shinuy hashem. I guess there's some things that's really
a שינוי השם, shinuy hashem, some things that's not so much a
שינוי השם. shinuy hashem. So this two by four, you know, you
look at it and you say, oh, there's a two by four
over there. You don't necessarily say, oh, it's a roof, right?
Whereas you would say this is a mat as opposed to saying
this is just a piece of leather. So you can't question me
on the beam. The beam really hasn't changed its name. So no
question on me. רב זירא אמר, Rav Zeira amar, רב זירא Rav
Zeira gives a different answer. שינוי החוזר לברייתו בשינוי השם לא הוי
שינוי. shinuy ha-chozer le-veryato be-shinuy hashem lo havei shinuy. So he's saying
well it depends if you can sort of if it can be
reversed, if it's a reversible שינוי. shinuy. So even if it's a
שינוי השם, shinuy hashem,
if it can be reversed, you know,
then it's not really enough of a שינוי. shinuy. So basically in
the case of a beam, let's say,
the reason why the guy doesn't get it בשינוי השם be-shinuy hashem
is not because so much a שינוי השם, shinuy hashem, but you
know, let's say, let's say my house were to fall down, right?
That two by four would just be the same two by four
as before. Again, like, you know, I didn't dye it, I didn't,
you know, sculpt it, there's no molding on it, there's no nothing,
you know, if I did some of that, that'd be different. All
I did was just like, you know, sort of use it as
one of many beams
and it's there. I didn't like cut it, I didn't trim it,
I didn't anything. So since it can be reversed, that's why he's
not קונה, koneh, right? Because meaning that's the whole point, right? So
that's the proof for רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
you know, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi can say, I mean meaning he
still agrees with רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, but from a different angle,
that a reversible שינוי השם shinuy hashem is not קונה. koneh. That's
you know, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would be right. And so
the only reason is תקנת השבים. takanat ha-shavim. So why doesn't he
have to return it? You're right. In a normal case he would
have to return it. But you know, we're not going to force
him to to, you know, to tear down the house to give
it back. That's why we say תקנת השבים. takanat ha-shavim. And otherwise,
you would have to give it back. Again, why would he have
to give it back? Because it's a reversible שינוי shinuy as opposed
to like let's say I you know like the the leather that
I made into shoes, right? Now it's a pair of shoes and
I'm walking around, he's like, give me back my leather. Like no,
that's a שינוי מעשה shinuy maaseh and a שינוי השם, shinuy hashem,
right? Now it's now it's shoes. So you know, let's say the
case of the tray, he doesn't have to give it back you
know like if you whatever it is, you
you know, worked it a little, you you know, embroidered, you stitched
it, whatever then it would be the same idea that that, you
know, if it's a שינוי מעשה, shinuy maaseh, it wouldn't, you know,
wouldn't get back but שינוי השם shinuy hashem if it's if it's
just a שינוי השם shinuy hashem that even if you build it
to something can be reversed, then you know then that's not שינוי
shinuy enough.
So that's so so that answers the the wood case.
So okay so basically his point is that a שינוי החוזר לברייתו
בשינוי השם shinuy ha-chozer le-veryato be-shinuy hashem is not really a שינוי.
shinuy. So the גמרא Gemara says is that really true? בשינוי השם
שאינו חוזר לברייתו מי הוי שינוי? be-shinuy hashem she-eino chozer le-veryato mi
havei shinuy? If it so basically if you know so the right
so if it can be reversed it is a שינוי... shinuy... I
mean if sorry if it can be reversed then it's not a
שינוי shinuy but if it can't be reversed then it isn't? So
is that really true? דהא צינור de-ha tzinor a a pipe מעיקרא
כפיסא והשתא צינורא. me-ikara kefisa ve-hashta tzinora. So let's say you make
a a wood pipe. So you
know you got a a block of wood so you hollow it
out and you know and you put it and attach it to
the pipe so now it's a pipe. Okay. ותניא צינור שחקקו ולבסוף
קבעו פוסל את המקוה קבעו ולבסוף חקקו אינו פוסל את המקוה. ve-tanya
tzinor she-chakako u-levasof kevao posel et ha-mikveh kevao u-levasof chakako eino posel
et ha-mikveh. So you'll know that you can't have מים שאובים mayim
sheuvim drawn water in a מקוה. mikveh.
So let's say I have a pipe, right? And you know
and this would forget the exact you know case as to how
this this is done. So like let's say I made a pipe
and then you know I took this piece of wood I hollowed
it out I attached it to whatever it is you know stuck
it to the ground you know so that the rain it'll go
so whatever rain water will like you know be channeled through you
know wherever it is both through this pipe and go into my
you know pit that I dug as a מקוה, mikveh, right? So
if I so if I did all that I took the wood
I hollowed it out I attached it to whatever and then you
know then attached it to the other pipe and you know then
now this is now attached to the ground, right? So it'll fill
up the ground the pit whatever.
So if I do all that then
then it is פוסל posel the מקוה. mikveh. But let's say I
stuck it into the ground as a piece of wood then I
hollowed it out and guess what, now it's a pipe, right? So
that's not considered a problem. That would not be פוסל posel the
מקוה. mikveh. So ואי
אמרת שינוי השם מילתא
היא ve-i amart shinuy hashem milta hi so if you're saying that
שינוי השם shinuy hashem is is you know is is good אפילו
קבעו ולבסוף חקקו נמי ליפסול. afilu kevao u-levasof chakako nami lifsol.
So why would it be in that second case if I attached
it to the ground and... hollowed it out
that it's good, why? It should be
פסול. pasul. Because you're saying that a שינוי השם shinui hashem that
is a שינוי השם shinui hashem and it's not reversible.
So if it's a שינוי השם shinui hashem and not reversible, you're
saying
that that's real שינוי, shinui, right? So if it's a real שינוי,
shinui, then it should be פסול מקוה pasul mikva because you know,
just like in the second case. What's the difference? Who cares if
I attached it to the ground and hollowed it out? It's a
שינוי. shinui. I did a שינוי. shinui. Why is that not a
problem of מים שאובים? mayim she'uvim? So he says שאני שאיבה דדרבנן
היא. shani she'iva de-rabbanan hi. So so
you know
drawn water is a rabbinic problem. So הכי אפילו
רישא נמי. hachi afillu reisha nami. So okay, so then so if
it's only a rabbinic problem then why are you splitting your rulings?
In one case you're saying it's a problem, one case you're saying
it isn't. If it's a problem, it should be a problem in
all cases, right? If it's not a problem, it should not be
a problem in either of the cases, right? So meaning in the,
you know, so if you're saying it's all דרבנן, derabbanan, shouldn't be
a problem even in the case where I, where, you know, was
a pipe to begin, where I, you know, even before where I
didn't attach it to the ground, where I just, you know, hollowed
it out and then attached it.
Why should that be a problem? You're saying it's a problem, why
should it be a problem? You're saying that the, you know, this
whole rabbinic, you know, thing, we're not going to be so strict
about it. So why are we strict about it in the first
case? Out to be consistent.
You know, it's either good or bad in all cases. So
he says no. He says התם איכא תורת כלי עליה בתילוש הכא
ליכא תורת כלי עליה בתילוש. hatam ika torat kelli aleih be-tillust hacha
leika torat kelli aleih be-tillust. No, I mean, the difference is, you
know, look at it when it was a, you know, at the
state where you're attaching it. In the first case, you made it
into a כלי, kelli, right? You know, as I said, you had
the wood, hollowed it out, before it was a piece of wood,
now it's a pipe. But in the second case, you know, in
the second case it wasn't a, it was just a piece of
wood. It was a block of wood which I stuck into the
ground, just a block of wood on the ground. Then I hollowed
it out. So the difference is, you know,
we're saying yeah, you know, it was דרבנן, derabbanan, but okay, we're
only going to take this דרבנן derabbanan so far. Like we're not
going to say it's always דרבנן, derabbanan, we're going to be lenient
in all cases. Look to see whether there's a כלי kelli or
not, you know, in its present state when you did all this.
If it was a כלי, kelli, you know, then we're going to
say it's a problem, and if it wasn't a כלי, kelli, we're
going to say that it's not.
So again, so in the first case where I took the piece
of wood, I hollowed it out and I attached it now, you
know, before I attached it, it was already a כלי. kelli. So
that's why it's a problem. On the second case, where it was
a block of wood and I stuck it into the ground, then
I hollowed it out, you know, when I stuck it into the
ground, it was not a כלי. kelli. So that's why it's not
a problem.
So anyway, what we're still maintaining is is that,
you know, that we can defend רב יוסף Rav Yosef who says
that יאוש ye'ush is not קונה koneh because רב יוסף Rav Yosef
was talking about like a just a case where there was יאוש
ye'ush and nothing else. You know, we can debate שינוי השם shinui
hashem and שינוי מעשה, shinui ma'aseh, you know, how far do you
take it, but you know, רב יוסף Rav Yosef can get out
of it and say, you know, all these questions you're asking me
from, it wasn't just a straight יאוש ye'ush case, there was some
sort of שינוי. shinui. Again, whether, you know, is it irreversible, does
it not need to be irreversible, you know, all these are details
we can work out, he's saying.
But you know, the core of my position, a straight יאוש ye'ush
has not been challenged yet. That it has no effect because all
your all your challenges are specific.
Okay? So again, so we've challenged רבא Rava who's managed to get
out of it with like a לחמץ בפסח le-chametz be-pesach case and
then a קרבן korban case. You know, again, רבא Rava is the
one that says יאוש ye'ush does have an effect and it seems
that those cases, you know, doesn't. Then we answered that, those are
specific cases. And we asked questions on רב יוסף Rav Yosef who
holds it doesn't have an effect with cases that seem it does,
but he answered all those by saying that it wasn't just a
straight יאוש ye'ush case, it was a יאוש ושינוי, ye'ush ve-shinui, שינוי
השם, shinui hashem, שינוי מעשה, shinui ma'aseh, whichever. מיתיבי הגנב והגזלן והאנסין
הקדישן הקדש ותרומתן תרומה ומעשרתן מעשר. meitivei ha-ganav ve-ha-gazlan ve-ha-annasin hikdishan hekdesh
u-terumatan terumah u-ma'asertan ma'aser.
So okay, so let's say there's no שינוי shinui at all, it
would seem. Like I just stole something and you know, I stole
your קרבן korban and I מקידש makdish it, right?
Or I stole your, you know, your wheat and I made it,
and I took תרומה terumah
or מעשר, ma'aser, you know, or טבל, tevel, whatever, you know, your
whatever it was, and I took תרומה, terumah, מעשר, ma'aser, made it
a קרבן. korban. It works, right?
Why would it work?
So the answer is, no.
הכא איכא שינוי השם מעיקרא טבל והשתא תרומה הקדש מעיקרא חולין והשתא
הקדש. hacha ika shinui hashem me-ikara tevel ve-hashta terumah hekdesh me-ikara chullin
ve-hashta hekdesh. Right? So again, רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, this is the
question on רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, right? Because if יאוש ye'ush is
not קונה, koneh, then why would a גנב ganav be able to
do anything? He again, he didn't do any, what change did he
do? The answer is he did do a שינוי. shinui. He did
a שינוי השם. shinui hashem. When I took your wheat, yes, same
wheat now as before, but it's not the same wheat now as
before. Physically the same wheat, but now it's called something else. You
took תרומה. terumah. You're not going to look at it, you're not
going to treat it the same way. תרומה terumah has its own
set of laws. You know, it's now תרומה terumah now. Before it
was just, you know, a regular sheep, now it's not a sheep
anymore, it's a קרבן. korban. So there's a שינוי השם. shinui hashem.
You can't ask me what יוסף Yosef would say on this kind
of a case where there's a שינוי, shinui, you know, my position
is if there's no שינוי shinui then it wouldn't have any any
effect. So meaning like, you know, let's say the גנב ganav didn't
do anything. He would have to give it back, right? So like
he wouldn't be קונה. koneh. Yeah.
Yes, if you have stolen
four species, then it's not valid to use, right?
Right, that's something yeah.
So isn't this using something stolen for a מצוה? mitzvah?
Right, I know, that I have that same I had that same
question,
but I think but I think that I don't know, I don't
know how you answer that. Like you know, I would think that
the and especially we're going to see something, you know, let's just
the גמרא's Gemara going to get back to us. But but yeah,
so I mean that's a good question. אמר רב חסדא אמר רב
יונתן: Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Yonatan: So now we're going to
have two teachings in the name of רב יונתן Rav Yonatan which
will be the exact opposite of one from the other. מנין לשינוי
שהוא קונה? Minayin leshinui shehu koneh? So, you know, the how do
we know that שינוי shinui works? שנאמר והשיב
את הגזלה אשר גזל. Shenemar veheshiv et hagezelah asher gazal.
That's so why did you need to say that? Of course you're
going to bring back the stolen object that you stole, not bringing
back a stolen object that you didn't steal, right? So what do
you need אשר גזל asher gazal for? מה תלמוד לומר אשר גזל?
Ma talmud lomar asher gazal? So it comes to teach you: אם
כעין שגזל יחזיר ואם לאו דמים בעי שלומי Im ke'ein shegazal yachzir
ve'im lav damim bei shalumei בעלמא בעי שלומי. be'alma bei shalumei. So
if it's still in the same state, then I give back the
object. But if not, then I have to pay him for it.
So that's what it's coming to teach you. So I have to
you have to make restitution either through דמים damim or through the
object, you know, depending on whether it is in the same state,
it would be one or the other.
So now you're saying that אשר גזל asher gazal means to make
this nuance? But no, אשר גזל asher gazal is coming to teach
something else. איבעי למיעט גזל אביו שאינו מוסיף חומש על גזל אביו.
Ibei leme'ut gezel aviv she'eino mosif chomesh al gezel aviv. So like
let's say, you know, someone stole something from his father and then
the father died, now the son wants to bring back the גזילה,
gezeilah, but the thing you know, but the point is that if
you have stolen something and admit to it, right, and not witnesses,
not טוען טענת גנב to'en ta'anat ganav and not עדים, edim, but
you just admitted it on your own, you have to pay the
קרן keren and the חומש, chomesh, right? So if that's if you
do it. But let's say you're no longer around and your children
are doing it for you, they just give back the object, they
don't have to pay the חומש. chomesh. They're admitting it, but it's
not the same person that's admitting it. So you don't say that
the that the heirs are like the person himself and have to
pay the חומש, chomesh, no, we don't say that. And you learn
all that from אשר גזל. asher gazal.
So no, but you can still learn both sets of laws, that
to get you out of the חומש chomesh and that you give
back the object versus דמים damim depending on what kind of a
state the object is in, because if you just want to learn
one of them, this law of not paying a חומש, chomesh, אי
הכי נכתוב רחמנא והשיב את גזלו אשר גזל. Ei hachi niktov rachamana
veheshiv et gezelo asher gazal. למה לי למכתב
והשיב את הגזלה אשר גזל Lama li limichtav veheshiv et hagezelah asher
gazal versus גזלו? gezelo? שמע מינה תרתי. Shema mina tartei. Okay, you
can learn both. So fine, so that's so his point is that
שינוי shinui is קונה, koneh, right? That's why you have to learn
אשר גזל. asher gazal. If it's the same state, then you give
it back. If not, then you don't, because a שינוי shinui would
be קונה. koneh. ואיכא דאמרי אמר רב חסדא אמר רב יונתן: Ve'ika
d'amri amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Yonatan: the opposite. מנין לשינוי שאינו
קונה? Minayin leshinui she'eino koneh? It's not קונה. koneh. שנאמר מאותו פסוק
והשיב את הגזלה. Shenemar me'oto pasuk veheshiv et hagezelah. You have to
bring back the גזילה, gezeilah, בכל מקום, bechol makom, I don't care
if it's the same way or not, if it's
the same state. So שינוי shinui isn't קונה, koneh, you still give
it back. What do you mean? והא כתיב אשר גזל? Veha ketiv
asher gazal? What about the אשר גזל? asher gazal? No, ההוא מיבעי
ליה על גזלו שלו שאינו מוסיף חומש ואינו מוסיף חומש על גזל
אביו. Hahu mibei lei al gezelo shelo she'eino mosif chomesh ve'eino mosif
chomesh al gezelo aviv. So אשר גזל asher gazal is not coming
to teach you that only if אשר גזל asher gazal if it's
the same state, that's coming to teach the law of that you
don't pay חומש chomesh for your father. So basically we, you know,
we have an answer to our מחלוקת, machloket, whether it's like רבי
יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, and and this is very well articulated in this
last point even, that that there's a that even a שינוי, shinui,
you know, forget about just straight יאוש, yei'ush, but even a שינוי
shinui we, you know, you may have to give back, depending, you
know, this teaching said both ways, you do or you don't, so
you know, and it's from the same פסוק pasuk even. So we
have an answer to our debate. So we're continuing. אמר עולא: Amar
Ulla: מנין ליאוש שאינו קונה? Minayin leyei'ush she'eino koneh? So how do
we know that יאוש yei'ush does not work, which would be like
רבי יוסף's Rabbi Yosef position? That it says שנאמר והבאתם גזול ואת
הפיסח ואת החולה, Shenemar vahasatem gazul ve'et hapisach ve'et hacholeh, right? Which
is what you were saying, that you know, you're bringing a stolen
קרבן korban to השם Hashem or a sick קרבן, korban, you know,
would God want it? No, he wouldn't want it, so meaning it's
not good. But here he's learning גזול דומיא דפיסח: gazul dumya de'pisach:
מה פיסח דלית ליה תקנתא? Ma pisach deleit lei takanta? As long
as this thing is is lame, right? You you know, you can't
bring a lame קרבן, korban, that's the end of it, like, you
know, let's say it's missing a leg, you can't like grow a
leg back. But you know, for the point is it won't get
better, like, you know, as long as it's in its state of
being lame, that's not an acceptable קרבן. korban.
מה פיסח דלית ליה תקנתא כלל אף גזול דלית ליה תקנתא.
Ma pisach deleit lei takanta
klal af gazul deleit lei takanta. Even a stolen object does not
have a תקנה. takanah. ולא
שנא לפני יאוש ולא שנא לאחר יאוש. Velo shna lifnei yei'ush velo
shna le'achar yei'ush. You cannot bring it. Doesn't make a difference, יאוש
yei'ush or not. So then the question would be, you know, what
do you do about that other case
before,
that about, you know, that the
הקדשן הקדש. hekdeshan hekdesh. So, you know, you might we'll we'll get
to it, we'll just bear with me, we're going to address that
right now. So
רבא אמר מהכא קרבנו ולא גזול, Rava amar mei hacha korbano v'lo
gozul, right? You can't bring an... so אם לא
קרבנו. im lo korbano. So you can only bring your קרבנו ולא
גזול. korbano v'lo gozul. So אימא eima when are we talking about?
אילימא לפני יאוש, ilima lifnei ye'ush, פשיטא? peshita? למה לי קרא? lama
li kra? So of course if it's before יאוש, ye'ush, you know,
I can't I can't bring it. That's for sure. We don't need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me that I can't bring it. אלא
לאחר יאוש ela l'achar ye'ush ושמע מינה יאוש לא קני. ushma mina
ye'ush lo kani. שמע מינה. shma mina. And I can learn from
here that יאוש ye'ush doesn't work either because that's what the פסוק
pasuk is telling you. If it's גזול, gozul, I don't care whether
there's יאוש ye'ush or not, you cannot bring it. But wait a
minute, if you remember how we started the day, we learned by
רבא Rava saying like oh we had this exact same thing and
רבא Rava asked on him, oh what are you going to do
about משכב? mishkav? We have משכב ולא גזול. mishkav v'lo gozul. Alright
you know so he said the whole case was different, that it
wasn't that I stole your חולין chullin animal and made it into
a קרבן, korban, but that I stole your קרבן korban animal, right?
So why so how are you learning from here
that it doesn't make a difference if it's יאוש ye'ush and we're
talking about he stole the חולין? chullin? You're the one that said
before רבא דאמר גזל קרבן דחבריה. Rava d'amar gazal korban d'chavreih. So
you know you gave a different answer before. Or now what you
know what are you giving this answer here now for? So ואיבעית
אימא הדר ביה, v'iba'is eima hadar beih, ואיבעית אימא חד מנייהו רב
פפא אמר. v'iba'is eima chad mineihu Rav Pappa amar.
Alright so he changed his mind and now he's learned now he's
trying to say that יאוש ye'ush makes no difference, right? Whereas before
he was trying to answer רבא Rava says that יאוש ye'ush does
make a difference, right? So you know that's why that was the
problem. So if he changed his mind, you know, he's giving this
different answer, or, you know, no רבא Rava didn't change his mind
and you know and you're seeing רבא Rava giving the same you
know giving different opinions, one of them is רב פפא. Rav Pappa.
So
anyway now we're seeing now at least from these past two
teachings we've seen that יאוש ye'ush does not have an effect. That's
exactly what we're trying to prove over here.
So
one second. I'm sure someone talks about this.
But I don't know what you do with this other case before.
I guess
I guess it was a case I guess the case is when
it's קרבנו ולא גזול. korbano v'lo gozul.
I'll have to think about it. I don't know. I'll have to
think about it.
It might depend on whether you stole it in its קרבן korban
state or its or in its חולין chullin state.
But then again if it was לפני יאוש lifnei ye'ush then you
know then we're saying that it's that it's so simple or
could say that it's a
מדרש midrash or maybe they're different teachings. You know like we had
a whole bunch of different תנאי tannai different teachings one way or
the other. So this so maybe one was going down on one
side of it and
but I don't know. Does the notes say anything?
Alright, but let's go on. I didn't think yeah I wasn't sure
we'd get this far. So מצות תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה mitzat tashlumei arba'ah
v'chamishah is only by a שור shor and a שה. seh. That's
it, right? Doesn't apply to a חמור chamor let's say. So I'll
write down the
פסוק pasuk שמות כ"א. Shemos Chaf-Alef.
Always better to do it from
here. Okay.
All
right. Well feel free to say anything while I'm writing this פסוק
pasuk down. So feel free to chime
in.
Okay. There was awkward silence in the recorder but I'm writing it
down. וטבחו
או
מכרו
חמישה u'tevacho o mecharo
chamishah always like to write a פסוק pasuk like getting the spelling
right
בקר תחת השור. bakar tachas hashor.
Okay, that is our פסוק pasuk which is the basis for ארבעה
וחמישה. arba'ah vachamisha. כי יגנוב איש שור או שה.
ki yignov ish shor o
seh. I
really
need another color. Let's see.
What other colors do we have? Any? Another color really makes all
the difference. Oh, all dried out. That is such a pity.
Oh well.
Let's see. Let's try one of these. Does this work?
Oh good. שור, או, שה. shor o seh
And then
שור shor,
or
שה. seh. Right? So it says it twice. That's the פסוק. pasuk.
So again, I'll read- I don't know if I first said the
whole
פסוק. pasuk. כי יגנוב איש שור או שה. ki yignov ish shor
o seh. So you steal an ox or a sheep וטבחו או
מכרו. utvacho o mechoro. So
you, you know, butcher it or you sell it. חמישה בקר ישלם.
chamisha bakar yeshalem. So you know, you pay- he pays in kind,
like you know, five cattle for the- תחת השור, tachat hashor, for
the ox, וארבע צאן תחת השה, ve'arba tzon tachat haseh, or you
know, four for the sheep,
including the principal. Yeah, including the principal. So you know, you pay
that too. So that's our basis for these פסוקים. pesukim. So the
question is, this is as our משנה Mishnah stated, restricted to just
a שור או שה. shor o seh, So the question is why?
ומאי שנא שור שור משבת? umai shena shor shor miShabbat? מה להלן,
mah lehalan, you know, 'cause it says in שבת Shabbat as well
that your- your שור shor needs to rest as well. למען ינוח
שורך וחמורך וינפש בן אמתך
והגר. lema'an yanuach shorcha vachamorcha veyinafesh ben amatcha vehager. So, you know,
these things need to rest. So and
just like שבת, Shabbat, it's not just like oh just my שור,
shor right?
So it's everything I own.
I can't work my, you know, whatever it is. I can't work
my birds, you know, nothing. מה להלן חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן, אף
כאן חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן. mah lehalan chayah va'of kayotze bahen, af
kan chayah va'of kayotze bahen. So why don't
we- why are we saying that שור או שה shor o seh
is very specific to שור או שה, shor o seh. right? Why
don't we say it means everything? I have to pay four or
five- we'll work it out, you know, what do you pay four
for, what do you pay five for, but you know, at least
it's not just the principal. So אמר רבא קרא שור ושה שור
ושה שני פעמים. amar Rava kera shor vasheh shor vasheh shenei pe'amim.
שור ושה אין מידי אחרינא לא. shor vasheh in midi acharina lo.
Because it says, you know, שור או שה shor o seh, once,
then חמישה בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה, chamisha bakar
yeshalem tachat hashor ve'arba tzon tachat haseh, right? So it says it
twice. So it's being very
specific. So meaning like, it didn't need to say it that way.
So now we're going to say what do you mean it didn't
need to say it? What could it have said, you know, for
you to say that? His point is, oh, this is like, you
know, extra so to speak, and we do this all the time.
Like, you know, you learn something that's extra that comes to teach
you this specific דין. din. So now we're going to say what's
extra? Because it could have said it differently. How could it have
said and the גמרא's Gemara going to go through a whole, you
know, back and forth as to what it could have said. And
then say no, it couldn't have said that because then you would
have thought this. Oh, it couldn't have said that because you would
have thought that. So meaning if this is the only thing it
could have said, right? Then we can't learn that it's just specific
to שור או שה. shor o seh? No, it's saying it because
like that's- it has to be said that way. And it's not
anything particularly meaningful to say it this way. And therefore we should
learn from שבת, Shabbat, and therefore it shouldn't just be for שור
או שה, shor o sheh, right? So you're saying because it says
it twice, that's very, you know, important. So I'm just going to
tell you it's not that important, you know. So now we're going
to go through it. Hopefully we'll get to the two dots. So
שור ושה shor vasheh okay, fine. So הי מנייהו? hei minayhu? אילימא
שור ושה דסיפא, ilima shor vasheh deseifa, meaning like this last part,
right? Over here. Like easier to- to see it when it's on
the board as opposed to try to, you know, think of it
in your mind. But if it would have said in the end
of it because what could it have said? ונכתוב רחמנא venichtov Rachmana
כי יגנוב איש שור או שה ki yignov ish shor o seh
mean keep the first part the same. So כי יגנוב איש שור
או שה ki yignov ish shor o seh fine. וטבחו או מכרו
חמישה בקר
ישלם
תחתיו וארבע
צאן תחתיו,
utvacho o mechoro
chamisha bakar yeshalem tachtav ve'arba tzon tachtav, right? It says חמישה בקר
ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה. chamisha bakar yeshalem tachat hashor
ve'arba tzon tachat haseh. Could have said תחתיו. tachtav. And we would
have known בקר's bakar for the בקר bakar case of שור shor
and צאן tzon is for the צאן tzon case of שה, seh.
right? So why does he say again שור או שה? shor o
sheh, Could have just said חמישה בקר ישלם תחתיו וארבע צאן
תחתיו chamisha bakar yeshalem tachtav ve'arba tzon tachtav instead of saying חמישה
בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן
תחת השה. chamisha bakar yeshalem tachat hashor ve'arba tzon tachat haseh. That's
his question. So אי כתב רחמנא הכי הוה אמינא בעי ישלומי תשעה
לכל
חד וחד. ei katav Rachmana hachi hava amina bei yeshalumi tish'ah lechol
chad vechad. You would have thought
since תחתיו tachtav is the same one, right? Same word תחתיו, tachtav,
right? שור shor, is very specific and שה seh. is very specific.
תחתיו, tachtav, you would have thought, you know, like very interesting thought,
I'd have to pay nine. In other words, I don't care whether
I steal a שור shor or a שה, seh, I have to
pay, I steal a שור, shor I pay five בקר bakar and
four צאן, tzon, right? I steal a שה, seh I pay also
five בקר bakar and four צאן. tzon. I would pay nine, right?
Because תחתיו, tachtav, what is תחתיו tachtav going on, right? תחתיו tachtav
was going on what we just mentioned before, שור או שה, shor
o sheh. right? Get it? Okay. I would have thought you have
to pay nine. What do you mean? וכי תימא אכתב תחתיו תחתיו,
vechi teima achteiv tachtav tachtav, right? He says, no, if it would
have just, if I would have just written תחתיו, tachtav, ארבע צאן
תחתיו, arba tzon tachtav, right? No, each תחתיו tachtav is going for
the respective שור או שה, shor o sheh? says and then, and
therefore חד תחתיו מיותר, chad tachtav meyater, right? And then it could
have, you know, then no, it's not מיותר, meyater, הוא מיבעי ליה
לדרשא אחרינא, hu miba'ei lei ledrashah acharina, דתניא יכול יגנוב שור ששוה
מנה ישלם תחתיו נגידין. detanya yachol yignov shor shaves maneh yeshalem tachtav
nigidin. Like let's say I stole, okay, so we have to pay
back four or five, but like, you know, what kind of four
or five? Maybe I'll give you like a bad four or five.
I stole like a nice healthy ox, I'll give you like, you
know, weakling oxes, oxen.
Maybe I can, you know, oxen like death's door, you know? Maybe
I can do that. No, so we want תחתיו תחתיו, tachtav tachtav,
you know, I really got to like, you know, give you back
like the same kind of quality that I stole. So,
so basically the point is it's not, it's not מיותר meyater because
I would have said if I would have done תחתיו tachtav then,
then I would think you have to pay nine. And what about
like this? No, you wouldn't. No, no, that
that's from another דרשא. drashah. Like you know, so it would have
said תחתיו תחתיו, tachtav tachtav, I would have figured it out. The
fact that it says תחתיו tachtav twice is does not mean specific
because I would have used that תחתיו tachtav for another purpose to
teach you to pay back good ones. So I have to pay
back four healthy sheep and five healthy oxen both for, you know,
stealing either a שור או שה. shor o sheh, So I still
would have thought that. So therefore it needs to say שור shor
and שה sheh, specifically, right?
So I wouldn't have thought that. Okay, so fine, so the end
of, so we need the end, right? Okay, fine, so let's try
from the beginning. Maybe we don't need the beginning, which is very
odd, to not have the beginning of anything when you, because the
beginning is telling you what you're talking about. But the גמרא Gemara
somehow thinks you could not have mentioned the beginning of the פסוק
pasuk and it would still figure out the same law. אלא שור
ושה דרישא מיותר? ela shor vesheh dereisha meyatar? דכתב רחמנא כי יגנוב
איש,
dechtav Rachmana ki
yignov ish, it doesn't say what, but כי יגנוב איש וטבחו או
מכרו חמישה בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה. ki yignov
ish utevacho o mecharo chamishah bakar yeshalem tachat hashor ve'arba tzon tachat
hasheh. The end will make clear what it is, right? I, I
steal, so I have to pay four for the צאן tzon and
five for the for the שור. shor, Right? So I could have
just said that. Why does it say שור או שה? shor o
sheh, So no, אי כתב רחמנא הכא, ichtav Rachmana hacha, if I
would have just said that, הוה אמינא דגנב תרי וטבחינהו. hava amina
deganav terei vetavachinhu. So I have to steal both a שור shor
and a שה, sheh, right? If I just would have said כי
יגנוב איש וטבחו
או מכרו, ki yignov ish utevacho o mecharo, right, if I don't
have the או, o, right, the או o is very important, right,
שור shor. או o, שה, sheh meaning one or the other. So
if I just, then I have to pay
five for the שור shor and four for the שה. sheh, Okay,
but like, but I'd still have to steal, you know, both of
them. Get it?
So okay, fine. So, you know, I understand four for one and
five for the other, so I slaughtered one, you know, I pay
four or five depending on what I slaughtered. But this would not,
this thing would not come into effect unless the specific thing if
I, if I steal a שור shor and a שה. sheh. What
if, what about stealing just one or the other? I wouldn't know.
What do you mean you wouldn't know? וטבחו כתיב לחד. utevacho ketiv
lechad. Fine, okay. But maybe הוה אמינא עד דגנב תרווייהו וטבחינהו או
מכרינהו, hava amina ad deganav tarvaihu vetavachinhu o mecharinhu, you know? So
I, but I still think I have to steal both, I'm not
getting out of this. I still think that I stole one of
them and maybe I and, you know, maybe I just sell
one. No, מכרו כתיב לחד. mecharo ketiv lechad. Fine, but still maybe
הוה אמינא עד דגנב תרי וטבח חד ומכר חד. hava amina ad
deganav terei vetavach chad umechar chad. Maybe I'd, I'd still think that,
you know, I have to steal two and, you know, slaughter one
and sell one. No, או מכרו o mecharo would have thought that.
או מכרו כתיב. o mecharo ketiv. I know that it applies to
just one being sold or slaughtered. But still, but I mean like
the גמרא Gemara is getting every, you know, גמרא Gemara is kind
of asking, getting to the question the way I phrased it, that
if I just would have said that, I don't know it applies
to just stealing one or the other, right? You wouldn't have thought
that I have to slaughter both. You wouldn't have thought that I
have to sell both. You wouldn't have thought I have to slaughter
one and, and or sell one and keep the other because, you
know, because everything is in the singular, right?
וטבחו מכרו, utevacho mecharo, right? But if it doesn't say שור shor
או o שה, sheh. I would think it would mean I have
to steal both, right? You haven't answered that question yet. ואימא אכתי
הוה אמינא עד דגנב תרווייהו וטבח חד משייר חד או מזבן חד
משייר חד. ve'eima akati hava amina ad deganav tarvaihu vetavach chad mishayer
chad o mezaven chad mishayer chad. Fine. אלא שור
דסיפא ושור ד
ela shor
deseifa veshor de... so okay fine. So the point is, we can't
say that both of these are extra. Now we can't say both
of these are extra, right? So something is extra to teach you
that it's specific to שור shor or שה, sheh, because if nothing
was extra then we should just say and abstract it from the,
into a regular שבת Shabbat case where it would apply to all
animals. Just like we can't work all animals, so too I can't
steal any animals and, you know, if I... chicken I'd have to
pay multiple times the value. Whatever again how you work that out
I don't know or how much three I don't know you know
like something more than one unless you're to say. So okay fine.
But maybe one of these is extra, meaning maybe one of these
is extra and then one of these is extra because I could
have said אלא שור ושה דרישא מיעטו Ella shor veseh deriesha miatu
דכתיב רחמנא dechtiv Rachmana כי יגנוב איש שור או שה וטבחו ומכרו
חמשה בקר ישלם תחתיו וארבע צאן תחת השה. ki yignov ish shor
o seh utvacho umacharo chamisha bakar yeshalem tachtav vearba tzon tachat haseh.
I could have said that. I mean it sounds very weird but
I guess the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks that that would have been
sufficient. So then you know the גמרא Gemara is saying that that
would have been perfectly fine to say so I don't need to
have you know both שור shor and שה seh in the beginning
and both שור shor and שה seh in the end. So the
fact that it does שור דסיפא ושה דסיפא שור דרישא ושה דרישא
למה לי שמע מינה שור ושה אין מידי אחרינא לא. shor desei-fa
veseh desei-fa shor deriesha veseh deriesha lama li shema mina shor veseh
in midei achrina lo. So we learn from this that it's just
specifically for those two animals. Whether you buy that דרשה drasha or
not, I don't know, but you know, nevertheless even if you don't
buy the דרשה drasha I mean it still seems that the law
makes sense as just for שור shor or שה, seh, you know
what I mean? You know the question may not have been the
best question, but it's
re-affirming what we kind of always at least I think intuitively understood
was just for these cases. All right, that is the end of
that. We are now a דף daf ahead, hopefully in good shape
for תשעה באב Tisha B'Av in a
week.
שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom.